Winther mss., 1934-1964 LMC 2333
Lilly Library
Winther mss.
1934-1964
Lilly Library
Winther, Sophus Keith, 1893-1983
LMC 2333
3 Boxes
The Winther mss., 1934-1964, consists of the papers of novelist and literary scholar Sophus Keith Winther, 1893-1983.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Sophus Winther was born in Søby, Denmark, June 24, 1893. Sophus, his parents Anton and Sine and his two brothers Rasmus and Søren came to the United States on April 16, 1895, and he was naturalized in 1900. He earned a B.S. from the University of Oregon in 1918, as well as an M.A. (1919) and a Ph.D (1927) from the University of Washington. Winter taught English at University of Washington for the rest of his career: as an instructor, 1927-1930; assistant professor, 1930-1934; associate professor, 1934-1940; and professor after 1940. He married one of his students, Eline Peterson, in 1925.
Winther's novels include The Realistic War Novel (1930) and Beyond the Garden Gate (1946). Three more, Take All to Nebraska (1936), Mortgage Your Heart (1937), and This Passion Never Dies (1939), form a trilogy about the life of an immigrant Danish family in Nebraska. Additionally, Winther was a scholar on the works of Eugene O'Neill (whom he befriended), and wrote Eugene O'Neill: A Critical Study, in 1934.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings; III. Miscellaneous Materials.
Scope and Content Note
The Winther mss., 1934-1964, consists of the papers of novelist and literary scholar Sophus Keith Winther, 1893-1983. Correspondents include Mary W. Barnes, Herbert Crombie Howe, Glenn Arthur Hughes, Ruth (Bryan) Owen, and Lee Paul Sieg. Writings include manuscripts of books, short stories, articles, and unfinished works. Included with the writings is a typescript of a poem written and signed by Read Bain.
Acquisition Information
Acquired 1965.
Authors, American --Correspondence; Winther, Sophus Keith, 1893-1983 --Correspondence.; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953.
- I. Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- II. Writings (Box 1)
  - Folders 2-3: Beyond the Garden Gate. T(carbon)D. 312p. some holograph changes and corrections. (Box 1)
  - Folder 4: [Class Four: A Novel in Four Acts] A.D. 178p. in pencil (Box 1)
  - Folder 5: Class Four: A Novel in Four Acts. T.D. (Box 1)
  - Folder 6: [Eugene O'Neill: A Critical Study] drafts of chapter titled The Sickness of Today A.&T.D. (Box 1)
  - Folder 7: Eugene O'Neill, A Critical Study. T(carbon)D. bound. [lacks chapter The Sickness of Today ] (Box 1)
  - Folder 8: Eugene O'Neill, A Critical Study. New York: Random House, c1934. galley proofs Duplicate Proofs for Index (Box 1)
  - Folders 9-10: The Fabric of Modern Literature. 2 drafts: T.D. 220p.; T(carbon).D. 220p. Cover label on carbon copy carries holograph note unpublished in red ink (Box 1)
  - Folders 11-12: Mortgage Your Heart. A.D. 414p. (Box 1)
  - Folders 13-14: Mortgage Your Heart. T(carbon)D. 285p. (Box 1)
  - Folder 15: [Sleep Quietly] not published T.D. 86p. (Box 1)
  - Folders 16-18: [Take All To Nebraska] Nebraska is My Home. T.&A.D.S. (Box 1)
  - Folder 19: Take All To Nebraska. T(carbon)D. p.1-137 (Box 1)
  - Folder 1: Take All To Nebraska cont. T(carbon)D. p.138-285. (Box 2)
  - Folder 2: Take All To Nebraska. proofs. (Box 2)
  - Folders 3-6: That Lonesome Road. T.D. 417p. originally titled Conquer We Must (Box 2)
  - Folders 7-8: This Passion Never Dies. A.D. p.1-258. (Box 2)
  - Folder 9: This Passion Never Dies cont. A.D. p.259-433. (Box 2)
  - Folder 10: Short stories. T and T(carbon)Ds. (Box 2)
  - Folder 11: Articles. T and T(carbon)Ds. (Box 2)
  - Folder 12: Notebook for Civil War novel. A&T.D. (Box 2)
  - Folder 13: [Waiting for the dam - Andersonville section of Civil War novel] T.D. p.412-531. (Box 2)
  - Folder 14: Untitled fragment re: Civil War. A.D. 15p. (Box 2)
  - Folder 15: Transcripts of reviews and extracts of reviews of works by S.K. Winther. T.Ds. (Box 2)
  - Folder 16: Young Author Faces Success, 1936 [poem by Read (sp?) Bain] T(carbon)D.S? 3p. (Box 2)
- III. Miscellaneous materials (Box 2)
  - Folder 17: Two photographs of Sophus Keith Winther (Box 2)
  - Folders 18-19: Newspaper clippings, ca. 1936-1964 (Box 2)
  - Folder 20: Scrapbook of clippings (Box 2)
  - Inscribed photograph of Carlotta O'Neill, Oct. 1933 (Box 3)
  - Inscribed photograph of Eugene O'Neill, Nov. 1933 (Box 3)
  - To Carlotta (inscription to final longhand script Mourning Becomes Electra) facsimile, no. 30. Inscribed by Carlotta Monterey O'Neill to Sophus Keith Winther. (Box 3)